Guide to the G. Norman Reis Papers, 1909-1946 CTC.1985.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
G. Norman Reis Papers
1909-1946
CTC.1985.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
3.5 linear feet
The Papers of G. Norman Reis primarily include materials from the Cap and Gown Club, a male musical comedy group of the University of Pittsburgh. The collection includes: programs, scripts, music, news clippings, financial records, correspondence, films, photographs, scrapbooks, personal papers and phonograph records from the period of 1909-1946. Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically.
Biography
G. Norman Reis was born on February 23, 1893 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He was a member of the class of 1916 at the University of Pittsburgh and served as a veteran contributor to the University's Cap and Gown Club - an all male organization devoted to the production of annual musical comedy shows. Beginning with the 1913 show, Prince of Sham, Reis collaborated with men, such as Gus Schnabel and Louis Fushan, on the book of lyrics used in many of the club's productions. In addition, he served on many committees and held offices in the club from the time of his earliest association until his death in 1958. These productions always used original books, lyrics, and music contributed by students at the University or by alumni members of the Cap and Gown Club. Many important figures had their earliest training and experience with the Cap and Gown including Regis Toomey, motion picture and musical comedy star, Woodman Thompson, a scenic designer, and Gene Kelly, dancer, instructor and director.
Reis was employed as a bacteriologist at U.S. Steel. He was an avid photographer, and, for a brief period, served as the official photographer for the Pitt Alumni Review as well as chairman and member of the editorial board. He died at the age of 65, three months after his retirement.
Arrangement
Series I. Personal Memorabilia
Series II. Dramatic Productions Other than Cap and Gown
Series III. Sheet Music
Series IV. Cap and Gown Productions
Series V. Cap and Gown Productions: Oversized Materials
Scope and Content Notes
The personal papers of G. Norman Reis pertain predominantly to the University of Pittsburgh's Cap and Gown Club, including souvenir and leaf programs, scripts, music, news clippings, financial records, correspondence, films, photographs, scrapbooks, and phonograph records. These categories are not complete in any of the cases. Besides individual music scores, music can also be found in some souvenir programs.
Items not associated with the Cap and Gown Club include Reis' script, Harmony Island, the Pittsburgh Athletic Association's 1917 drama club presentation, and unidentified scripts. There are also materials on other all-male musical comedy groups such as Mask and Wig (University of Pennsylvania) and Triangle Club (Princeton University) programs and/or sheet music, University of Pittsburgh fight songs, including a victory song with words by Reis, miscellaneous music, as well as several issues of the Pitt Alumni Review for which Reis served as chairman and member of the editorial board.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Helen Whitlinger in 1985.
Previous Citation
G. Norman Reis Papers, 1909-1946, CTC.1985.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
G. Norman Reis Papers, 1909-1946, CTC.17, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Cap and Gown Club Records, 1908-1978, CTC.1980.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically. Selected photographs were scanned and added to the University of Pittsburgh Historic Photographs collection.Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at [URL].
Cap and Gown Club (Pittsburgh, Pa.).; Kelly, Gene, 1912-1996; Pittsburgh Athletic Association.; Princeton University. Triangle Club.; Reis, G. Norman, 1893-1958; Thompson, Woodman; Toomey, Regis, 1902-; University of Pennsylvania. Mask and Wig Club.; Bacteriologists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College and school drama, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College theater -- United States; Student activities -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater; Theater -- United States; Theater programs
- Personal Memorabilia, I.
  Scope and Contents note
  There are three folders of Personal Memorabilia consisting of news clippings from 1941 through 1946, several copies of the Alumni Review and Pitt Panther.
  - News Clippings (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Review, 1941-44, 1946 (Folder 2)
  - Pitt Panther, March 1930 (Folder 3)
- Dramatic Productions Other than Cap and Gown, II.
  Series II contains items concerning dramatic productions other than the Cap and Gown Club.
  - Harmony Island Script and Publicity (Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Scripts (Folder 5)
  - Mask and Wig (U. of Penna.) Program (Folder 6)
- Sheet Music, III.
  This series contains miscellaneous music that was not used for Cap and Gown productions. The four folders of material include a booklet of Songs of the University of Pittsburgh, Pitt Victory Song with words by G. Norman Reis and Louis M. Fushan and music by Benjamin Levant, and music from the Mask and Wig (Folder 8) and Triangle Clubs at the University of Pittsburgh and Princeton (Folder 9).
  - Songs of the University of Pittsburgh, Pitt Victory Song (Folder 7)
  - There's No Place like Your Arms from All Around the Town (Folder 8)
  - Happy the Day from Take It Away, Can it Be True? from Fol-De-Rol., 1936 (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Sheet Music (Folder 10)
- Cap and Gown Productions, IV.
  This series includes materials related to the Cap and Gown Club listed chronologically by production. It contains souvenir and/or leaf programs, scripts, phonograph records, musical scores, news clippings, other miscellaneous promotional material, and 16-millimeter films. Each of the productions contains some or all of the materials previously mentioned. The 16-millimeter films are shelved independently from their corresponding productions at the end of the series. It also includes financial records and correspondence pertaining to the Club's productions. Items marked with an asterisk (*) have the music for the production in the program.
  - When Pitt Was Young - Programs and Scripts (Folder 11-12)
  - Little Suffragettes - Scripts (Folder 13)
  - The Maxixe Girl - Programs and News Clippings (Folder 14)
  - Suite 16 - Programs and Musical Scores (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - The Diamond Girl - Musical Scores: The Diamond Girl lyrics only. (Folder 3)
  - Mary Grow Round* - Programs (Folder 4)
  - Yip-Yip* - Programs and Scripts (Folder 5-6)
  - Manhattan Preferred* - Programs (Folder 7)
  - What's Up* - Programs and Scripts (Folder 8-9)
  - The Silver Domino* - Programs, News Clippings, and Scripts (Folder 10-11)
  - All to the Point* - Programs, News Clippings and Nixon Theatre Program with Advertisement (Folder 12)
  - Hello Again* - Programs (Folder 13)
  - In the Soup* - Programs and Scripts (Folder 14-15)
  - Out for the Count* - Programs and Scripts (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Trailor Ho!* - Programs and Scripts (Folder 3-4)
  - Pickets, Please* - Programs and Alumni Review (Folder 5)
  - At Your Service - Programs, News Clippings, Alumni Review, and Scripts (Folder 6-7)
  - At Your Service - Musical Scores (Folder 8-9)
  - At Your Service - Phonograph Record: Nothing is too Perfect for You (side 1) Diary of Dreams (side 2) - 2 copies (Folder 10-11)
  - Snap Your Fingers - Programs and Musical Scores (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Head Over Heels* - Programs, Scripts, and Musical Scores (Folder 3-5)
  - Kilroy Is Here - Programs and Scripts (Folder 6-7)
  - Cap and Gown Music 1940 - Phonograph Record (Folder 8)
  - Financial Reports - Receipts and expenditures for, 1931-1941 (Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: from Louis M. Fushan to G. Norman Reis (Folder 10)
  - Films -- All to the Point, (contains shots of Gene Kelly) and Silver Domino, 1932-1933 (Folder 11)
  - Films -- Hello Again, 1934 (Folder 12)
  - Films -- In the Soup, 1935 (Folder 13)
  - Films -- Out for the Count, 1936 (Folder 14)
  - Films -- Trailer Ho!, 1937 (Folder 15)
  - Films -- Unidentified Cap and Gown Production (Folder 16)
- Cap and Gown Productions: Oversized Materials, V.
  This series includes oversized materials related to the Cap and Gown Club listed chronologically by production. It contains musical scores, photographs, and scrapbooks. Each of the productions contains some or all of the materials previously mentioned.
  - Little Suffragettes Music: You're the Girl For Me; At the Movies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Maxixe Girl Music: The Lad in the Uniform (Folder 2)
  - The Maxixe Girl Photographs (Folder 3)
  - At Your Service Photographs (Folder 4)
  - The Red Moon and Miss Mannequin Scrapbook (Folder 5)
  - Yip-Yip Scrapbook: compiled by Ted Savage (Folder 6)
  - Manhattan Preferred Scrapbook: compiled by Ted Savage (Folder 7)
  - Hello Again Scrapbook (Folder 8)
  - Pickets, Please! Photographs (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Snap Your Fingers Photographs (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Folder 3)